A Guide to the Papers of the McGill-Mahone Families
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the McGill-Mahone Families 1771-1919
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
1627
This collection consists of ca. 5600 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited in the Library on March 12, 1943, and was made a gift to the Library by William H. McGill of Charlottesville, Virginia, and Henry P. McGill of Petersburg, Virginia, on October 23, 1979.
Scope and Content Information
The McGill-Mahone collection is comprised of items generated by the McGill and Mahone families of Petersburg, Virginia. The collection includes business and personal correspondence, financial papers, bound financial and business records, legal documents, student class notebooks, and miscellaneous printed material. The contents of the collection concern three general topics: 1) papers pertaining to the management of property owned in Virginia by James and John Dunlop of London, England, and administered by Robert Leslie of Petersburg, Virginia; 2) papers pertaining to the tobacco firm Watson & McGill, in Petersburg, Virginia, of which Robert Leslie, R. L. Watson, and John McGill were the initial partners; and 3) papers of William Mahone pertaining to his Virginia political and business career after the Civil War.
The first group of papers, those relating to James and John Dunlop of London, England, date from 1771 to 1847. Included are land deeds for property purchased in Virginia by James and John Dunlop, primarily in Petersburg and Chesterfield County; indentures for shares in the Upper Appomatox Canal Company purchased by James and John Dunlop; bills of sale for slaves owned by Dunlop; financial records for "Roslin," an estate near Petersburg owned by Dunlop; and letters to Robert Leslie from James Dunlop regarding Leslie's management of Dunlop's legal and financial affairs in Virginia. Many of these letters concern tobacco trade between the United States and England. There is also some correspondence between Leslie and Dunlop's executors following Dunlops death ca. 1843.
The second group of papers, 1848-1918, consist of the personal and business papers of John McGill of Petersburg, Virginia, son-in-law of Robert Leslie. McGill was a partner in the tobacco firm of Watson and McGill, which operated in Petersburg, Virginia, and carried on both a foreign and domestic trade in tobacco. The financial papers include correspondence, bills, and orders, as well as numerous bound financial volumes. Also included in this section are financial papers and correspondence regarding "Dunedin," an estate owned by John McGill.
Personal correspondence in this section is comprised primarily of letters written by William M. McGill and Henry McGill to their parents, Mr. and Mrs. William L. McGill, between 1916 and 1918. The letters were written while the two were attending various schools in Virginia, including Virginia Military Institute, Cluster Springs Academy, and Shenendoah Valley Academy.
The third group of papers pertain directly to General William Mahone and his business and political activities from 1870 to 1895. Mahone, a former Confederate general, was a controlling force in Virginia politics from around 1870 until 1883, when his party, the "Readjusters," lost control to the "Conservative Democrats." A division among Virginia politicians occured in the 1870's, when those who supported a reduction of Virginia's pre-war debt ("Readjusters") opposed those who felt Virginia should repay its entire debt plus interest ("Funders"). Mahone and his followers successfully supported several Readjuster candidates for the governorship and legislature, with Mahone being appointed a United States Senator in March 1881. Mahone's control of Virginia politics lasted until 1883, when the Readjusters lost majority control in the legislature, followed by the election of Fitzhugh Lee as governor in 1885. During this period, Mahone also served as president of the Atlantic, Mississippi and Ohio Railroad, a consolidation of three largely state-owned short lines between Norfolk and Bristol into one privately-owned railroad, authorized by legislation passed in 1870 by the General Assembly.
Mahone's correspondence concerns Virginia politics, including the southwestern region; the railroad and mining interests owned by the railroad; and the Richmond Whig, which Mahone controlled through railroad patronage. Correspondents include James Branch, C.E. Evans, John Everett, E. Fitzgerald, Abram Fulkerson, George W. Grice, Robert W. Hughes, J.B. Hurt, J.A. Johnson, John W. Johnston, James Lawson Kemper, Nathaniel B. Meade, E.C. Robinson, John M. Robinson, George Rye, John C. Shields, J.H. Slaughter, C. Maurice Smith, Charles W. Statharn, James C. Taylor, W.F. Taylor, W.H. Turner, and R.F. Walker. In addition, there are several letters from each of the following persons: John S. Barbour, Frank S. Blair, William E. Cameron, John W. Daniel, Jubal A. Early, William C. Elam, Fitzhugh Lee, Harrison Holt Riddleberger, Waller Staplers, C.W. Stringfellow, and Gilbert C. Walker. Miscellaneous printed material and maps of mineral deposits in southwestern Virginia and property owned by Mahone in Washington, D.C., are also present.
The bound volumes consist primarily of the business records of the tobacco firm Watson & McGill from ca. 1830 to 1920. These include daybooks, journals, ledgers, order and shipping registers, invoice books, and letter books. Two tobacco workbooks are present with weekly time records of women employed in stemming tobacco. Also included in the bound volumes are several financial volumes regarding the management of James and John Dunlop's property in Virginia by Robert Leslie. There is a detailed journal, 1829-1831, of "Roslin," a property in Virginia owned by the Dunlops, which lists financial transactions and includes an inventory of the Roslin property, as well as a daily work record of the slaves and hired hands.
Other bound volumes include a journal of the minutes of the Smyth County Pomona Grange meetings, 1875-1879; a journal of surveying done by A. F. Bonham; and eight class notebooks, 1876-1888, of William Mahone, Jr., R. Butler Mahone, and William L. McGill.
Contents List
- Letter Books of Watson and McGill, Tobacco Merchants 1846-1915, 17 volumes
  - 1846-1849
    A-1
  - 1882-1883
    A-2
  - 1902-1904
    Indexed. A-3
  - 1904-1905
    Indexed. A-4
  - 1905
    Indexed. A-5
  - 1906
    Indexed. A-6
  - 1906-1907
    Indexed. A-7
  - 1907-1909
    Indexed. A-8
  - 1909-1910
    Indexed. A-9
  - 1910-1914
    A-10
  - 1911
    Indexed. A-11
  - 1911-1912
    Indexed. A-12
  - 1912
    A-13
  - 1912
    A-14
  - 1912-1913
    Indexed. A-15
  - 1913-1914
    Indexed. A-16
  - 1913-1915
    Indexed. A-17
- Business Records, 1821 - 1919, 37 volumes
  - Daybook (Petersburg, Virginia) 1821-1824
    B-1
  - Register of tobacco shipments 1821-1825
    Indexed. B-2
  - Invoice book 1821-1826
    B-3
  - Ledger 1826-1833
    Indexed. B-4
  - Journal (Roslin, Virginia; with inventory of property, including slaves) 1829-1831
    B-5
  - Cashbook 1838-1842
    B-6
  - Ledger 1838-1895
    B-7
  - Journal 1848-1858
    B-8
  - Ledger 1848-1875
    Indexed. B-9
  - Ledger (with TMsS, 1863 May 1, notice of liquidation of Watson and McGill and Co.) 1854-1871
    B-10
  - Journal (Petersburg, Virginia) 1858-1875
    B-11
  - Invoice book 1860-1889
    B-12
  - Journal (Petersburg, Virginia) 1861-1871, 1879
    B-13
  - Journal 1866-1870
    B-14
  - Journal (Petersburg, Virginia) 1871-1876
    B-15
  - 1877-1882 Journal (Petersburg, Virginia)
    B-16
  - Ledger 1877-1889
    Indexed. B-17
  - Order and shipping register 1879-1882
    B-18
  - Journal/Ledger/Register of bonds 1879-1887
    B-19
  - Receiving register for loose tobacco 1880
    B-20
  - Petty cash book 1883-1884
  - Register of bills payable and recivables by Inge and Mahone 1880-1884
    B-21
  - Daybook (Leaf tobacco) 1882-1884
    B-22
  - Journal (Petersburg, Virginia) 1882-1888
    B-23
  - Journal 1888-1894
    B-24
  - Printed share certificates for the Eldorado Mining, Manufacturing & Improvement Co. of Virginia ca. 1890
    B-25
  - Ledger 1889-1905
    Indexed. B-26
  - Journal (Petersburg, Virginia) 1894-1901
    B-27
  - Journal (Petersburg, Virginia) 1901-1907
    B-28
  - Register of Shipments 1905-1914
    B-29
  - Ledger 1905-1914
    Indexed. B-30
  - Cashbook 1906-1914
    B-31
  - Journal 1908-1914
    B-32
  - Checkbook of Watson & McGill 1911-1914
    B-33
  - Invoice Book 1913-1914
    B-34
  - Checkbook of Watson and McGill 1913-1916
    B-35
  - Checkbook of Watson and McGill 1916-1919
    B-36
  - Index n.d.
    B-37
- Course notes (University of Virginia) and Miscellaneous, 1875-1904. 9 volumes.
  - Minutes of the Smyth County Pomona Grange meetings 1875-1879, C-1
    The latter half of the volume was subsequently used to record "Accounts of surveying done by A.F. Bonham", 1892-1904
  - University of Virginia Notebook of William L. McGill 1887-1888, C-2
    Agricultural chemistry, English language
  - University of Virginia Notebook of William Mahone, Jr. 1876-1878, C-3
    Anglo-Saxon, French history, chemistry
  - University of Virginia Notebook of R. Butler Mahone 1878-1879, C-4
    Natural philosophy
  - University of Virginia Notebook of William L. McGill 1887, C-5
    English literature
  - Notebook of William L. McGill ca. 1887, C-6
    Latin
  - Notebook of William L. McGill ca. 1887, C-7
  - University of Virginia Notebook of William L. McGill ca. 1887, C-8
    Logic
  - Notebook of William L. McGill 1888, C-9
    English language
- Journal 1828 (Box 1)
- Account book 1830-1831 (Box 1)
- Tobacco workbook 1830-1833 (Box 1)
  2 items
- Ledger 1873
- Check book 1876-1882 (Box 1)
- Memorandum and Account Book 1882 (Box 1)
- Account Book 1887-1894 (Box 1)
- Account Book - Mrs. J. McGill 1902-1906 (Box 1)
- Check books of Mrs. Helen L. McGill 1903-1912 (Box 1)
- Copy of Indenture between A. Bolling and wife and Charles Duncan selling land on Appamatox River 1771 Jul 6 (Box 2)
- Copy of Indenture between Wm. Thompson and Charles Duncan selling about 30 acres of land on Appamatox River 1773 Feb 15 (Box 2)
- Indenture deeding 30 acres of land on Appamatox River by Wm. Thompson and Charles Duncan 1773 Feb 15 (Box 2)
- Citizenship papers of James Dunlop, copy 1792 (Box 2)
- Shares in the Upper Appomatox Company 1800 (Box 2)
- Indenture deeding land in Petersburg, Virginia, James and John Dunlop 1803 Dec 17 (Box 2)
- Deeds to land in Patrick County 1805 (Box 2)
- Deed to land in Petersburg, Virginia and deeds to shares in Appamatox Company 1807 (Box 2)
- 5 shares in Upper Appomatox Company 1808 (Box 2)
- Indentures and deeds 1809 (Box 2)
- Advisability of building road to Roslin and sale of stock in Upper Appamatox Company (Indenture) 1810 (Box 2)
- 4 Indentures - Shares in Upper Appamatox Company by John and James Dunlop 1811 (Box 2)
- Indenture purchasing shares in Upper Appamatox Co. by John and James Dunlop and contract for sale of Negro woman and two children 1812 (Box 2)
- 3 Indentures - Purchase of land north of Pocahontas by Joseph Rowleth; Purchase of land by Joseph and John Dunlop north side of canal and Purchase of land by Joseph Rowleth on north side of Pocahontas 1813 (Box 2)
- Indenture purchasing land in Chesterfield County by James Dunlop 1914 (Box 2)
- 2 Memoranda of agreement between John Brandon and James Dunlop over land exchanged, a result of straightening road in Chesterfield County 1815 (Box 2)
- Court order on road to be built and Indenture, Purchase of land by James Dunlop 1817 (Box 2)
- Land Sales 1819 (Box 2)
- Land and financial papers 1820 (Box 2)
- J. Blackwood to Rev. Levenworth ca. 1820 (Box 2)
- Memorandum on repairs ca. 1820 (Box 2)
- Receipts; Purchase of shares in Upper Appomatox Co.; Purchase of land 1821 (Box 2)
- Power of Attorney given Thomas Shepherd and Robert Leslie for James and John Dunlop 1821 Mar 1 (Box 2)
- Notes from John Dunlop n.d. (Box 2)
- Land deeds, etc. 1822 (Box 2)
- Power of Attorney - Messrs. Newton & Laurie & Co. to Shepherd and Leslie 1823 Oct 3 (Box 2)
- Agreement releasing Wm. B. Harwood from responsibility to bond - Leslie for John Dunlop 1823 May 26 (Box 2)
- Sale of Negro women and 6 children 1825 Mar 14 (Box 2)
- Financial Statements - John and James Dunlop 1825 Jul 1 (Box 2)
- Power of Attorney - John Dunlop to Robert Leslie 1826 Aug 18 (Box 2)
- Land Deeds 1827 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Robert Leslie 1828 (Box 2)
- Purchase of 190 acres in Chesterfield County on Appomatox River by Charles Duncan 1771 Feb 8 (Box 2)
- Purchase of 30 acres in Chesterfield County on Appomatox River by Wm. Thomson 1755 Aug 1 (Box 2)
- List of lands purchased of Thomas Reid, remaining unsold 1811 27 Feb (Box 2)
- Land grant by Commonwealth of Virginia to James Dunlop 1826 May 29 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Robert Leslie from James Dunlop 1829 (Box 2)
- Price list of Tobacco showing charges, also current price list at Liverpool 1829 Jan 29 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Robert Leslie from James Dunlop 1829 Feb (Box 2)
- James Dunlop to Robert Leslie 1829 Mar 30 - 1829 Aug (Box 2)
- List of Real Property belonging to James Dunlop delivered to L. Colguhoun by Robert Leslie 1829 Oct 23 (Box 2)
- The courses of two tracts of land owned by Dunlop-Pollock Co. n.d. (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Robert Leslie 1830 (Box 2)
- Letter Press Copies of letters - James Dunlop to Ludovert Colguhoun 1830 (Box 2)
- Kerr Caskies & Co. to Robert Leslie 1830 June 12 (Box 2)
- W. Hender[son] to Colguhoun and Plat of Roslin 1830 July 12 (Box 2)
- Balance sheet of Leslie & Brydon's books 1830 Jul 12 (Box 2)
- Letters to Henderson, Colguhoun and Mrs. Calvin at Roslin ca. 1830-1832 (Box 2)
- Leslie Correspondence n.d. (Box 2)
- Letters to Henderson, Colguhoun, Leslie and Brydon 1831 (Box 2)
- Purchase of 3 1/2 acres in Chesterfield County 1831 Jun 17 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Robert Leslie 1832 Jan (Box 2)
- R. Richie to Wm. Henderson 1832 Jan 16 (Box 2)
- Correspondence to Wm. Henderson 1832 Feb (Box 2)
- Correspondence to Robert Leslie 1832 Apr (Box 2)
- Account 1832 Apr (Box 2)
- Correspondence to Robert Leslie 1832 Aug, Sep, Oct (Box 2)
- Correspondence to Robert Leslie 1833 Jan - Feb (Box 3)
- Sale of the Brig Thomas and William1833 Mar 11 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Robert Leslie and financial receipts 1833 Mar, Apr, May (Box 3)
- Correspondence to Robert Leslie 1833 Jul - Dec (Box 3)
- Account of sales of cargo of Brig Thomas and William1833 Dec - 1834 Feb (Box 3)
- Wm. Oxley to Robert Leslie n.d. (Box 3)
- Vouchers, Receipts, etc. 1834 (Box 3)
- Papers of the Brig Thomas and William1834 (Box 3)
- "List of Persons Composing the Crew of the Brig Thomas and William of Petersburg..." 1834 Nov 14 (Box 3)
- Finance Papers and Receipts 1835 (Box 3)
- Roslin Cash Book 1836 (Box 3)
- Correspondence to Robert Leslie 1837 Apr, Jul (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Robert Leslie - Finance, Business 1838 (Box 3)
- Power of Attorney - James Dunlop to Robert Leslie and Timothy Oxley 1838 Mar 28 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Robert Leslie 1839 (Box 3)
- Memorandum of Bonds of Rep. of Texas transferred to Robert Leslie 1840 Dec 15 (Box 3)
- Notes n.d. (Box 3)
- Proprietors of Oaks Ware House Account with Inspectors 1842 (Box 3)
- Tobacco price report 1842 Dec 31 (Box 3)
- Correspondence and Business Papers 1843 (Box 3)
- Robert Leslie Cash Notebook 1843-1844 (Box 3)
- Land Deeds 1844 (Box 3)
- Robert Leslie Correspondence 1845 (Box 3)
- Robert Leslie Correspondence - Financial, Business 1846 (Box 3)
- Memorandum n.d. (Box 3)
- Leslie Correspondence 1847 (Box 3)
- Account sheets at death of James Dunlop 1847 Oct 1 (Box 3)
- Dr. Laurel Hill - Account 1848-1853 (Box 3)
- E. J. H. and J. Lawford to Robert Leslie 1848 Aug 18 (Box 3)
- Masonic authorization for Robert Leslie n.d. (Box 3)
- Fire and Marine Insurance Co., List of stockholders 1849 May 1 (Box 3)
- Correspondence to Robert Leslie 1849 (Box 3)
- Scraps [1850s] (Box 3)
- Lease 1850 Jun 3 (Box 3)
- Correspondence and Business Papers of Robert Leslie 1851 (Box 3)
- Apprenticeship Indenture 1852 Mar 2 (Box 3)
- John B. Simmons account w/Robert Leslie 1852-1859 (Box 3)
- Financial Papers 1853 (Box 3)
- Leslie Correspondence 1853 (Box 3)
- Correspondence on South Side and Appomatox R.R. 1853-1865 (Box 3)
- Notes and Memoranda n.d. (Box 3)
- Leslie Correspondence 1854 (Box 3)
- Illinois lands belonging to the estate of James Dunlop 1854 Nov 1 (Box 3)
- List of James Dunlop's debts in Virginia n.d. (Box 3)
- Correspondence, etc. of Robert Leslie 1855 (Box 3)
- Notes on finances 1855-1856 (Box 3)
- John Hinton to Robert Leslie 1856 Jan 31 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, etc. of Robert Leslie 1856 (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Robert Leslie; Disposition of James Dunlop's Will; Powers of Attorney 1857 (Box 3)
- Robert Leslie Correspondence n.d. (Box 3)
- Robert Leslie Correspondence 1858 Jun - Dec (Box 3)
- Correspondence to Robert Leslie, Watson and McGill Co. 1859 (Box 4)
- Accounts 1860-1867 (Box 4)
- Account n.d. (Box 4)
- $200 Confederate Bills [withdrawn] 1862-1864 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Robert Leslie 1863 (Box 4)
- Barney Bros. and Co. bill to John McGill 1863 (Box 4)
- Certificate of Insurance 1865 Nov 13 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Robert Leslie and John McGill 1865 (Box 4)
- List of lands belonging to the Estate of James Dunlop n.d. (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Robert Leslie, Accounts 1866 (Box 4)
- Account book: Accounts w/John McGill 1866-1870 (Box 4)
- Leslie, Watson and McGill Co. Correspondence 1867 (Box 4)
- 3 unsigned letters concerning Dunlop Estate 1867 (Box 4)
- Tax receipts - John McGill 1868 (Box 4)
- Tax Receipts - John McGill 1869 (Box 4)
- Tax Receipts - J. McGill 1869 (Box 4)
- Pamphlet 1869 (Box 4)
- Bill: Booth and Summers to Leavenworth 1870 May (Box 4)
- Receipts 1870 (Box 4)
- Extract from letter on Trade Mark n.d. (Box 4)
- Receipts 1871 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of Watson and McGill 1871 (Box 4)
- Receipts 1872 (Box 4)
- Leavenworth and McGill account with Leavenworth 1872 (Box 4)
- Correspondence on Tobacco - Watson and McGill 1874 (Box 4)
- E. G. Ward to R. Towne and Co. 1875 Dec 14 (Box 4)
- Complaints on Tobacco quality 1877 Nov - Dec (Box 4)
- Benefit Certificate: Knights of Honor to Bro. Wm. Crosse 1877 Nov 15 (Box 4)
- Account of Tobacco Sales 1877 Dec 10 (Box 4)
- Tax Receipt 1878 (Box 4)
- Robert Leslie Executors Account Book 1878-1897 (Box 4)
- Correspondence - John McGill 1879 (Box 4)
- Business Correspondence and Papers 1881 (Box 4)
- McGill and Jones Certificate Executors of Estate of Robert Leslie 1881 Apr 13 (Box 4)
- Cards and Memoranda n.d. (Box 4)
- McGill and Watson - Correspondence and Business Papers 1882 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of John McGill 1882 (Box 4)
- Bills of [John] McGill (especially from hotels) 1882 (Box 4)
- Financial Accounts n.d. (Box 4)
- Watson and McGill Correspondence 1883 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of John McGill 1883 (Box 4)
- Watson and McGill Correspondence 1884 (Box 4)
- Balance Sheets - Watson and McGill 1884-1912 (Box 4)
- Tobacco Order 1885 (Box 4)
- John McGill - Eye prescription 1885 (Box 4)
- Tobacco classifications n.d. (Box 4)
- Correspondence and Business Papers of Watson and McGill 1886 (Box 4)
- Statement 1886 Apr - May (Box 4)
- Wm. L. McGill - Passport to Germany 1886 Aug 30 (Box 4)
- Tobacco Reports 1887 (Box 4)
- Statements of J.E. Moyler and Co. to Watson and McGill 1887-1888 (Box 4)
- Correspondence of John McGill 1888 Dec - 1889 Jan (Box 4)
- Reports on lands owned by heirs of Robert Leslie 1880, 1881, 1889 (Box 4)
- Wm. L. McGill's Comission in Va. Volunteers 1890 Nov 15 (Box 5)
- Correspondence of John McGill 1890-1891 (Box 5)
- William Mahone to Mrs. McGill 1892 (Box 5)
- Mahone to Wife 1893-1894 (Box 5)
- Correspondence - John McGill 1893-1895 (Box 5)
- Check Book 1898 (Box 5)
- McGill vs. Western Bank of Canada 1898 (Box 5)
- Watson and McGill Correspondence 1899-1900 (Box 5)
- Correspondence of Cameron Dunlop (dealer in Tobacco) to Watson and McGill 1901 (Box 5)
- Watson and McGill Correspondence 1902 (Box 5)
- Bank Book of Mrs. Helen L. McGill 1902-1908 (Box 5)
- Correspondence of Cameron Dunlop to Watson and McGill 1903 Jan - Oct (Box 5)
- Account: McGill with Thos. Branch 1903 Sep - Dec (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence of Watson and McGill 1903 (Box 5)
- Correspondence of John McGill - Bills 1904 (Box 5)
- Watson and McGill vs. Otto Peycke and [Bohn], Hamburg, Germany 1904-1905 (Box 5)
- Bills - John McGill 1905 (Box 5)
- Accounts 1905 (Box 5)
- Correspondence of Watson and McGill 1905 (Box 5)
- Memorandum n.d. (Box 5)
- Contract between John McGill and Eddie Pegram 1906 (Box 5)
- Correspondence of Watson and McGill on Tobacco 1906 (Box 5)
- Tobacco Orders to Watson & McGill 1907 (Box 5)
- Tobacco Orders 1908 (Box 5)
- Letters to John McGill at Greenbriar, White Sulphur Springs, to Wm. Watson 1909 Jul - Sep (Box 5)
- Tobacco orders 1909-1910 (Box 5)
- John McGill at White Sulphur Springs to Wm. Watson 1910 Jul - Sep (Box 5)
- Auction 1911 Mar 22 (Box 5)
- John McGill at White Sulphur Springs to Wm. Watson 1911 Jul - Sep (Box 5)
- Contract and correspondence between Watson and McGill and J.M. Cranor 1912 Mar (Box 5)
- Machinery for drying tobacco 1912 Jun 21 (Box 5)
- John McGill at White Sulphur Springs to Wm. Watson 1912 Jul - Sep (Box 5)
- Memorandum 1914 Nov - Dec (Box 5)
- Memoranda n.d. (Box 5)
- Correspondence of Wm. L. McGill 1915 (Box 6)
- Testimony of Cadets Conrad and McGill concerning fight (incomplete) at Virginia Military Institute [1915] (Box 6)
- Correspondence in connection with dismissal of McGill from Virginia Military Institute 1915-1916 (Box 6)
- Correspondence in connection with dismissal of McGill from Virginia Military Institute 1915-1916 (Box 6)
- On McGill's dismissal from Virginia Military Institute- fragile 1915 Dec 21 (Box 6)
- Correspondence of John and Wm. L. McGill 1916 Jan - Jul (Box 6)
- Correspondence of Wm. L. McGill 1916 Jan - Jul (Box 6)
- Correspondence of Wm. L. McGill 1916 Sep - Dec (Box 6)
- Letters of Wm. M. McGill to his parents of Petersburg, Virginia: Letters of Henry McGill to his parents of Petersburg, Virginia; Letter to William L. McGill from Arthur Kyle Davis, St. of Petersburg, Virginia. includes progress reports from Cluster Springs Academy and from Virginia Military Institute; Miscellaneous letters to Wm. L. McGill from Cluster Springs Academy and Virginia Military Institute. 1916 (Box 6)
- Letters of Wm. M. McGill at Virginia Military Institute to his parents; Letters of Henry McGill at Shenandoah Valley Academy to his parents; Progress reports from Virginia Military Institute and Shenandoah Valley Academy to W.L. McGill includes various accounts and correspondence with Virginia Military Institute and Shenandoah Valley Academy 1917 Jan - Mar (Box 6)
- Letters of Wm. M. McGill at Virginia Military Institute to his parents; Letters of Henry McGill to his parents; Progress report from Virginia Military Institute to Wm. L. McGill 1917 Apr - Jun (Box 6)
- Correspondence of Wm. L. McGill 1917 Jan - Dec (Box 6)
- Letters from Wm. M. McGill to his parents; Letters from Henry McGill to his parents; Miscellaneous letters to Wm. L. McGill includes Progress Reports of Wm. M. McGill at Virginia Military Institute, and Correspondence with Augusta Military Academy and Shenandoah Military Academy 1917 Jul - Dec (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous and undated; Clippings 1917 (Box 6)
- Letters of Henry McGill to his mother and father of Petersburg, Virginia 1918 (Box 6)
- Correspondence of Wm. L. McGill 1918 (Box 6)
- Tour of Petersburg 1825 (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 6)
- Tobacco pictures n.d. (Box 6)
- Broadsides, etc. n.d. (Box 6)
- Clippings 1852 (Box 7)